<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act repealing all acts of Parliament or Committee made for the late unlawfull engagement, and ratifying the protestation and opposition against the same.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1157A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183954</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529201</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178896</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05226)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178896)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2774:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act repealing all acts of Parliament or Committee made for the late unlawfull engagement, and ratifying the protestation and opposition against the same.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler, Printer to the Kings most excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Dated on p. 1: At Edinburgh the sixteen day of January the yeer of God one thousand six hundred fourty nine years.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: William Scot, Cler. Parl.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: blurred print with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Parliament. --  Committee of Estates --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Repeal of legislation --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178896:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178896:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ACT Repealing all ACTS of PARLIAMENT OR COMMITTEE, Made for the late unlawfull Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ratifying the PROTESTATION AND OPPOSITION againſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:178896:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178896:2"/>
            <head>ACT Repealing all Acts of Parliament or Committee, made for the late unlawful Engagement, and ratifying the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, and oppoſition againſt the ſame.</head>
            <head type="sub">At <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the ſixteen day of January the yeer of God One thouſand ſix hundred fourty nine years.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Eſtates of Parliament preſently conveened in this ſecond Seſsion of the ſecond Trienniall Parliament by vertue of an Act of the Committee of Eſtates, who had Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from the laſt Parliament for conveening of the Parliament, Taking to their moſt ſerious conſiderations (after ſo great judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and deliverances on Gods part, and after ſo So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn an Acknowledgment and Covenant renewed on their part) the Acts of the laſt Seſsion of Parliament, Beginning the ſecond of <hi>March,</hi> and ending the tenth of <hi>June</hi> 1648. And of the Committee of Eſtates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178896:3"/>
               <hi>September</hi> laſt, and the proceeding of the Forces raiſed by them in the firſt and ſecond Levie, and theſe brought out of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and of the Committees of War in the ſeverall Shires appointed by them with the grounds, reaſons, and pretences therefore whither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Kings conceſsions at the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> or ſet down in their Declarations, as in the fourth and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, ſixteen, twenty ſix, twenty ſeven Acts of the laſt Parliament, and in their Declaration to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> emitted by the Committee of Eſtates the twenty eight day of <hi>June</hi> laſt when their Army went into <hi>England,</hi> in eſtabliſhing, carrying on, and proſecuting the late Engagement againſt the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and raiſing the firſt and ſecond Leavie, in preſſing the ſame at home by unlawful Bands and cruel Plunderings; and in rejecting all Warnings, Petitions, Remonſtrances from the Kirk Judicatories, and from Shires at home; and all Remonſtrances and offers of Treaty made from the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> by their Commiſsioners, in refuſing to declare the Kings Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsions at the Ile of <hi>VVight</hi> unſatisfactory to them, in trampling under foot the Liberties of the Church at home, in invading of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing of their Towns, and marching through their Counties, and aſſociating with the Malignant party there; in returning after their defeat to <hi>Scotland,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their oppreſsion in this Kingdom, and invaſion of <hi>England;</hi> and to that end in the raiſing of new Forces, ſending Commiſsions to the claſſed Incendiaries of this Kingdom (who by ſtanding Acts of Parliament were debarred from all Truſt, for their joyning in the late Rebellion) and in many other ways, acts, and deeds
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:178896:3"/>cuting their deſigne at home and abroad. And conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſeveral offers and deſires made by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> for continuing the Peace and Union, and the many earneſt and humble Petitions from ſeverall Shires, and the moſt part of Provinciall Synods and Presbyteries; and the juſt and neceſſary Deſires, Remonſtrances and Declarations of the Commiſsioners of the Church to the Parliament and Committee, with their unſatisfactory Anſwer thereunto; and the Papers paſt betwixt the late General Aſſembly and the Committee, and the Diſſent and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations entred in the Parliament by a great number of every Eſtate, and that of ſuch as hath been moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental and conſtant in this Cauſe ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And withall, taking to their ſerious conſideration the manifold ſolid reaſons againſt the Engagement, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Remonſtrances of the Commiſsion of the Kirk given in to the Parliament; And of the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Declaration of the late General Aſſembly, and the reply of their Commiſsioners, demonſtrating from the Word of God the unlawfulneſſe of the ſaid En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and evidencing the many Breaches of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Treaties of Peace, the many wrongs done to the Liberties of the Church, and oppreſsions of the people of God, and many other unlawfull ingrediences in the matter, manner, nature and effect of that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement: And therefore denouncing Gods judgment againſt it, And warning the people to do their duty for the Cauſe of God and to the Covenant againſt all lets and impediments. All which was ſeconded ſo ſpeedily and immediately by Gods own hand, ſtirring up the hearts of his conſcientious People to the reſolution of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178896:4"/>oppoſing ſo great a defection from the Cauſe and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. And by his performing the Counſell of his Meſſengers and confirming the words of his ſervants in the defeat of that Army, and their overthrow in <hi>England</hi> with their aſſociats in <hi>England:</hi> As alſo in ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of the remainder of that force returned unto <hi>Scotland,</hi> and joyned with theſe who at home were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaving this Kingdom, and in deveſting them with their own conſent by Treaty (with ſo little blood) of all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force and exerciſe of State-power, untill the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of this Parliament. And the Eſtates pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſeriouſly the great neceſsity, and manifold rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons preſſing the Proteſters in Parliament with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the conſtant Covenanters throughout the Land, To make that oppoſition in Armes, ſo tryſted, directed and countenanced by Gods own good hand upon them as is more expreſſed in the Declaration of the Committee of Eſtates of the ſeventh of <hi>October</hi> laſt, and Information of the Kirk, publiſhed to the view of the world upon the ninth day of <hi>October</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore, and for many other reaſons and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, convincing them in their conſciences, That the foreſaid proceedings of the late Parliament and Committee in the appointing and proſecuting that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement againſt <hi>England,</hi> and in the oppreſsing of the Church in her Liberties, and of the good People throughout the Land in their perſons and eſtates: And which is moſt of all, in their conſciences by force and violence, cauſing the people to ſin, after they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by their Petitions the ſame was againſt the light of their conſciences, were unlawfull before God, and againſt his Word, were breaches of the Solemn League
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178896:4"/>and Covenant (which being an Oath to GOD ſo neceſſary is not alterable by any humane Authority) and of the Treaties betwixt the Kingdoms, and under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of doing for Religion, for the King, for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, did really tend (as doth now more appear) to the ruining of Religion, undoing of the King, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Kingdoms; And which in few moneths hath more waſted the ſubſtance of this Kingdom, and eſpecially of the wel-affected, then all our former troubles; And hath led out a forced multitude to ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or ſlavery, with ſo great reproach and diſgrace to the Nation, and occaſioned a powerfull Army to enter the bowels of this Kingdom in put ſuit of their enemies who had invaded <hi>England,</hi> to the great endangering of this Kingdom, and ſo laying the Land open, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it lyable to the guilt and miſerie of an unjuſt and offenſive War, drawing down Gods judgements, and expoſing us and our poſterity to invaſion from our neighbour Kingdom, if God in his providence had not remedied the ſame. As the Eſtates of Parliament have made before God a <hi>Solemn Acknowledgement</hi> of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſins and breaches of the Covenant, and a Solemn Ingagement to all the duties therein contained, Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe which do in a more ſpecial way relate unto the dangers of theſe times, that Gods judgement drawn upon the Nation by ſuch a ſinfull courſe by a prevalent party of the repreſentative body may be removed, and the like in time coming prevented, So alſo that all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Law at home for proſecuting of theſe courſes; And that all pretence of quarrell from abroad againſt this Nation for the ſame may be taken away; And to teſtifie the firm reſolution and earneſt deſire of this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178896:5"/>Kingdom to preſerve inviolably the Union betwixt the Kingdoms. The Eſtates foreſaids, do hereby finde and declare the Kings Conceſsions at the Iſle of <hi>VVight,</hi> and late Declarations emitted by the Parliament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, to be unſatisfactory to them, and deſtructive to the Cauſe and Covenant: And doth diſclaim, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, annull, repeal, and declare to be void and of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effect the Acts after mentioned, as being in themſelves from the beginning unjuſt and unlawfull, and contrary to the Word of GOD, and Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and large Treaty betwixt the Kingdoms, The fourth Act intituled, <hi>Act anent the reſolutions of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, concerning the breaches of the Covenant and Treaties betwixt the Kingdoms of</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> England, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for reparation thereof.</hi> The ſixt Act, intituled, <hi>Act for putting of the Kingdom in a poſture of VVar for defence, and conſtituting the Committees of VVar of the ſeverall Shires.</hi> The ſeventh Act, intituled, <hi>A Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parliament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>to all his Majeſties good Subjects of this Kingdom, concerning their reſolutions for Religion, King, and Kingdoms in purſuing the Ends of the Covenant.</hi> The eight Act, intituled, <hi>Deſires of the Parliament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>to the Honourable Houſes of the Parliament of</hi> England. The ninth Act, intituled, <hi>Act anent the Levies of horſe and foot to be put out by the Shires and Burghs, and the Liſt of the Colonels, with their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi> The eleventh Act, intituled, <hi>Act in favours of the out-reikers of Horſe and Foot.</hi> The ſixteenth Act, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>A Letter from the Parliament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>to the ſeverall Presbyteries within the Kingdom.</hi> The eighteenth Act, intituled, <hi>Act anent the Oath to be taken by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of VVar in the ſeverall Shires.</hi> The nineteenth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178896:5"/>Act, intituled, <hi>Act and Ordinance concerning the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons within the Kingdom, for proviſion of the Forces there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and adding of two moneths Maintenance to the former five:</hi> The twenty Act, intituled, <hi>Act for raiſing of Troops.</hi> The twenty third Act, intituled, <hi>Act Ordaining all Miniſters to exhort their people to obedience to the Laws of the Kingdom, and aſſuring theſe Miniſters of their ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, during their lifetimes.</hi> The twenty fourth Act, intituled, <hi>Act Ordaining the whole Members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Noblemen, Barons, Burgeſſes, and all other Subjects and inhabitants of the Kingdom to ſubſcribe this Act for defence of the lawfulneſſe of this Parliament, and obedience to the Acts thereof.</hi> The twenty ſixt Act, intituled, <hi>Act and Declaration of Parliament, and Anſwers to the ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations from Synods and Presbyteries.</hi> The twenty ſeventh Act, intituled, <hi>Act and Declaration of Parliament, in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Petitions preſented to them from ſome Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees of War of Shires.</hi> And all other Acts, or parts, or clauſes of any other Act of the laſt Parliament publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and grounds and pretences thereof, in ſo far as they import, the approbation, purſuance, or furtherance of the ſaid late unlawfull Engagement. And this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall clauſe, is declared to be alſo ſufficient for repealing and annulling of them, as if the tenour thereof were herein inſert, wherewith the Eſtates diſpenſe.</p>
            <p>Siclike the Eſtates annuls, reſcinds and repeals among the imprinted Acts, the Commiſsion granted to the cloſe Committee, concerning <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which divers Members of Parliament entred their diſſent and Proteſtation, the Commiſsions gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and other Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; The Ordinance in favours of theſe that proteſted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178896:6"/>in <hi>Fyfe,</hi> and <hi>Hadingtoun;</hi> The Ordinance for giving thanks to theſe, who in the ſeverall Shires preſented Petitions, or writ Letters for encouraging the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to go on in the Engagement: The Act anent the Colledge of Juſtice, and their Colonell. The Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent the Lord <hi>Cochrane,</hi> Laird <hi>Garthland,</hi> and <hi>Alexander Crawfurd</hi> their going to <hi>Ireland:</hi> The Act ratifying the Acts of Committee made in the receſs of Parliament; and all other unprinted Acts, or clauſes of unprinted Acts, grounds, and pretences thereof, in ſo far as they import the approbation, purſuance or furtherance of the ſaid late unlawfull Engagement. And this generall clauſe is declared to be als ſufficient for repealing, and annulling them as if the tenours thereof were herein inſert.</p>
            <p>In like manner the Eſtates of Parliament condemns, annuls and reſcinds all the Acts of the Committee of Eſtates, contained in the table ſubjoyned to this Act, And all other Acts or parts, or clauſes of any other Acts of the ſaid Committee of Eſtates, grounds and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences thereof, in ſo far as they import the approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, purſuance, or furtherance of the ſaid late unlawful Engagement; and this generall clauſe is declared to be alſo ſufficient for repealing and annulling of them as if the tenour thereof were herein inſert, wherewith the ſaids Eſtates diſpenſe.</p>
            <p>And in like manner, do annull, condemn, and repeal all Acts made, and deeds done by the former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Committee of Eſtates, contrary to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kirk, or any wayes encroaching upon the ſame, in particular theſe which follow; Firſt, their emitting of Declarations, containing things highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178896:6"/>Religion, not only without advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the GENERAL ASSEMBLY and their Commiſsioners, but contrary to their expreſs De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, Supplications, Remonſtrances and Declarations, declaring the ſame to be dangerous and deſtructive thereto, eſpecially the reſtoring of the King to honour, freedom and ſafety, without ſufficient ſecurity firſt had from him for ſecuring of Religion, as is more fully expreſſed in the Deſires and Repreſentation of the Commiſsioners of the Generall Aſſembly: Secondly, the putting of an unſound gloſs in the cloſe of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Parliament upon the Covenant, and Acts of the Generall Aſſembly, in theſe things that concern our duties to the King, as is clearly holden forth in the Repreſentation of the Commiſsion of the Aſſembly. Thirdly, The making proviſion for ſecuring of the ſtipends of ſuch Miniſters as ſhall be cenſured for their concurring in, or preaching for the unlawfull Engagement againſt <hi>England:</hi> Fourthly, their groſs miſrepreſenting of the proceeding of the Commiſsion of the Generall Aſſembly by the Parliaments Letter of <hi>May</hi> the eleventh, to the ſeverall Presbyteries, and endeavouring to incenſe them againſt the Commiſsion of the Generall Aſſembly, and to pre-poſſeſs with prejudices the Commiſsioners to the following Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Fifthly, the taking upon them in the Act and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Parliament, commonly called the Band, to judge and determine ſuch things without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe of the Kirk, wherein the Aſſemblies of the Kirk have a ſpecial intereſt of an antecedent judgement, as who are enemies to Religion, and who not, and what are the moſt fit and neceſſary remedies for preſerving of the ſame. Sixthly, their depriving of the Generall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178896:7"/>Aſſembly and their Commiſsioners of the liberty of Printing, by putting an inhibition to the contrary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Printers, under the pain of death, againſt ſeverall Acts of Parliament, Declaring and confirming the Kirks Libertie and Priviledge of Printing: And ſiclike diſclaims and condemns their impious uſurpation in calling in the printed Copies of the Cauſes of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn univerſal Faſt and Humiliation, indicted by the Commiſsioners of the Aſſembly, and inhibiting of the Printer to give any out of his hands, thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to interrupt the obſerving of the Faſt by the want of information of the Reaſons and Cauſes thereof; And alſo annuls, and repeals, diſclaims and condemns, all and ſundry other Acts made, and deeds done by the ſaid Parliament or Committee of Eſtates, or by their Authority that may infer any prejudice to Religion, or the power, priviledges and Liberties of the Kirk which we are bound by ſo many ſtrong Bands and Solemn obligations to maintain: And ſiclike annuls and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinds all Acts of Committees of Shires, or Burghs Royall, or of Regality, Barony Courts, or other Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories whatſoever made in purſuance of that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement; And Ordains all the ſubſcribed Copies of the Band, condemned by the Generall Aſſembly, to be brought in to the parliament or Committee of Eſtates, to be diſpoſed of as they ſhall think fitteſt: And all other Acts, grounds, and pretences thereof, in ſo far as they import the furtherance, or purſuance of the ſaid late unlawful Engagement. Likeas the Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, upon the manifold abovementioned grounds more fully related in the Declaration of the Committee of Eſtates, and Information of the Kirk, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:178896:7"/>that the Proteſtations of the Members made in Parliament, and their Oppoſition ſince by defenſive Armes for the ſafety of the Covenant, Cauſe, and themſelves, from ruine againſt ſo great a defection, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on with ſo great oppreſsion; and their proceedings in the Treaty at <hi>Stirling,</hi> diveſting the ingagers with their own conſent, of power and force which they had in their hands; and their aſſurance given by the Act of the ſixt of <hi>October</hi> to the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> for debarring of the Authors and Abettors of that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement from places of publick Truſt or Power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their conſent, which was demanded by their forces as the leaſt ſatisfaction and ſecurity before their removal and their proceedings by publick Acts in the purſuance of theſe two Treaties, to ſeclude thoſe who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred in the Engagement from power in Judicatories, Armies, or places of Truſt untill the determination of a Parliament were lawful in themſelves, and neceſſary for them according to the condition of affairs. Therefore the Eſtates of Parliament did allow, approve of and confirm the Diſſent and Proteſtation made in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by many Faithfull Members of each Eſtate, whereof the tenour follows. <q>Whereas the draught of a Declaration hath been read concerning the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Covenant in matters of Religion, and the Demands to be made for remedy and reparation thereof, the dangers to Religion, and the duties whereunto we are obliged by Covenant, for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and Uniformity in Religion, and the ſecurity to be had for the eſtabliſhing the ſame: upon which grounds alſo a War is principally founded: And whereas we have earneſtly deſired and inſiſted, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178896:8"/>there may be no proceeding to any determination con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſaid Declaration, before the Commiſsion of the General Aſſembly be firſt conſulted therein: We do hereby enter our Diſſent from proceeding to the determination of matters ſo highly concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, without the adviſe and concurrence of the Kirk, as a preparative of moſt dangerous conſequence to Religion, and deſtructive to the Liberties of the Church; as contrary to the Nationall and Solemn League and Covenant, and to the known Laws and conſtant practiſe of this Kingdom. And we do Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that we may not be included in any ſuch Vote or Reſolution, but may be free of all the guiltineſs, confuſions, diſtractions, and evils whatſoever that may follow thereupon to Religion, the King, this Kirk and Kingdom, and the union betwixt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſiclike allowes the riſing of ſuch Shires and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who joyned in Armes for oppoſing of the ſaid en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and reſcuing the Kingdome from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the forces under the command of the Earle of <hi>Crawford,</hi> Earle of <hi>Lanerk,</hi> and <hi>George Monro,</hi> and their proceedings in purſuance thereof, and alſo ratifies the late Treaty at <hi>Stirling</hi> and <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> upon the twenty ſixt and twenty ſeventh of <hi>September</hi> laſt; and ſiclike allowes the Treaty and Engagement to the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> by their anſwers of the ſixt of <hi>October</hi> laſt, for debarring of the ingagers from publick truſt in this Kingdome without their conſent. Siclike the two Acts of Committee of the twenty ſecond of <hi>September,</hi> and fourth of <hi>October;</hi> and the Act of the ninth of <hi>November,</hi> all made for debarring of theſe who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178896:8"/>concurred in the late Engagement, from the exerciſe of publike places or truſt untill the determination of this Parliament. Likewiſe the Declaration of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates concerning their proceedings in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the late unlawfull Engagement againſt <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> of the date the ſeventh of <hi>October</hi> laſt, publiſhed to the world; and the Act of the ſaid Committee for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the publike acknowledgement, and renewing of the Covenant, and the Act of the Committee of the fourteen of <hi>October</hi> laſt: All which the Eſtates of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as is aforeſaid doe allow, confirm, and ratifie in all the Heads, Clauſes, and Articles thereof. And this generall clauſe is declared to be als ſufficient for ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and confirming the ſaids Acts and Clauſes thereof, as if the Tenors of the ſame were here particularly inſert; Wherewith the Eſtates foreſaids doe hereby diſpenſe. Followes the liſt of the Acts of the Committee of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates for advancing the Ingagement. Act for diſplacing of ſuch of the Committee of Warre as would not take the Oath. Act for ſending the forty thouſand pounds to <hi>Ireland.</hi> Warrand to quarter upon the deficients in the unlawfull Ingagement. Letters to ſeverall Shires for advancing the Levie. Letters, Commiſſions, Deſires, and Anſwers for bringing the forces out of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Warand for impriſoning the Magiſtrates and Counſell of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> for their deficiencie in the Levie. The Oath to be taken by the Committee for maintaining the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of Parliament. Approbation of the Earle of <hi>Callendar</hi> and Generall Major <hi>Middleton</hi> for their baſe, cruell and unnaturall proceedings, againſt the honeſt and conſcientious people that met at <hi>Machline Moore</hi> for their own defence, whilk was not done without the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178896:9"/>baſeneſſe and treachery of ſome. Protection to the Captain of <hi>Clanrainold,</hi> and <hi>Maclene</hi> excommunicate bloody Rebels. Act for ſtopping of printing; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Kirks liberty. Letter to the army in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to proceed againſt theſe that refuſed to obey their Orders for the Ingagement, as enemies to Religion, King, and Kingdomes. Warrand to Duke <hi>Hammilton</hi> to Gariſon the houſes of the beſt affected in the Weſt. Warrand to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Argyle</hi> to deliver <hi>Lamond.</hi> Commiſſion to the Earle of <hi>Crawford</hi> to command the forces that come out of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Act for drawing Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayes againſt the Miniſters, and for continuation of their proceſſe untill a new citation. Commiſſion to Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Dowglas</hi> of <hi>Blakerſtone</hi> (a prime claſſed malignant, for having hand in the rebellion of <hi>James Grahame</hi>) to uplift the fines of the honeſt men in the Weſt, for being at <hi>Mauchlin Moore.</hi> Commiſſion to young <hi>Maclene</hi> who had been in the Rebellion to be a Collonell. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration anent the Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> and his army. War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand to Duke <hi>Hammilton</hi> to invade <hi>England.</hi> The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Committee of Eſtates anent the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of invading of <hi>England.</hi> Act for repaying monies ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced for the Ingagement. Letters to <hi>Lambert</hi> to joyn with Duke <hi>Hammiltons</hi> army. Warrand to Mr. <hi>George Halyburton</hi> to borrow mony in <hi>England</hi> upon publick faith unlimited. Letters to the King and Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ſhewing their intentions in the Engagement, lent with Mr. <hi>George Halyburton.</hi> Act taking of Sir <hi>John Drummonds</hi> reſtraint. Commiſſion to <hi>Lauderdale</hi> to ſecure Berwick. Severall anſwers of the Committee of Eſtates, and meſſages to the Generall Aſſembly moſt unſatisfactory. Protection of <hi>Patrick Leſlie</hi> from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178896:9"/>the cenſure of the Generall Aſſembly. Impriſonment of <hi>Greenhead</hi> and Colonell <hi>Scot.</hi> Approbation of the Lord <hi>Cochrane,</hi> and Laird of <hi>Garthlands</hi> proceedings in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Act allowing of twenty thouſand pounds to Lord <hi>Cochrane,</hi> and Laird of <hi>Garthland.</hi> Act for the new Levie of one thouſand five hundred horſe, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of ane Guard to the Prince. Commiſſion to <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intoſch</hi> for ane Gariſon to the houſe of <hi>Innerlochie.</hi> Warrand to levie Troopes for advancing the Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Commiſſion to Duke <hi>Hammilton</hi> to be Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Berwick,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Carlile.</hi> Precept to Generall Major <hi>Robert Monroe</hi> for ane thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound ſterling. Warrand to the Commiſſioners to deliver victuall to <hi>Seaforth, Machlene,</hi> and <hi>Macdonald,</hi> who were in the former rebellion for entertaining of their force. Warrand to diſcharge the Gariſons of <hi>Dowart Moy,</hi> and others; whereof the Marqueſſe of <hi>Argyle</hi> had the keeping. Commiſsion to <hi>Macconnel</hi> to depute another in his place, himſelf &amp; all his friends being in the Rebellion. <hi>Macconnel</hi> diſcharged of his former Rebellion, and imployed without finding cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Act pardoning <hi>Macleane,</hi> notwithſtanding of the Acts of the third and eight of <hi>February</hi> 1648. whereby he is declared to have forfeited their pardon. Charge to the Marquis of <hi>Argyle</hi> to deliver <hi>Lamond</hi> under the pain of Rebellion, and his eſcheat to fall. Warrand for removing all out of the Abbey. Act approving the caſhiering of Sir <hi>Dugald Campbell</hi> of <hi>Auchinbreck,</hi> and <hi>VVilliam Campbell</hi> from their places in <hi>Argyles</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and placing others therein, for their not concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the Engagement. Act diſcharging the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of <hi>Linlithgow</hi> from the exerciſe of their calling,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178896:10"/>in admitting a Miniſter, and ordaining the Kirk doors to be locked. Letters relating to the Engagement. Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for raiſing of the <hi>Atholl</hi> men, who had been in the Rebellion. <hi>VVilliam Gordon</hi> of Monymore, an active and bloody Inſtrument in the Rebellion, ſet at liberty freely. Warrant for publiſhing the Committees Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations. Princes Declaration and Information of publick proceedings. Earl of <hi>Airlie</hi> diſcharged of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen moneths Maintenance. The Petition from the Committee of <hi>Stirling</hi> Shire, anent their Miniſters committed. New Commiſsions and Warrants, Earl of <hi>Seaforth, Makgleud,</hi> Sir <hi>James Macdonell,</hi> contrary to ſtanding Acts of Parliament. Commiſsion to the Earl of <hi>Lanerk</hi> to be General. Severall Letters expreſſing they would not live, and out live that Engagement. <hi>Lauderdails</hi> inſtructions, to bring Forraign Forces out of <hi>France, Holland,</hi> or elſewhere. Letters to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of <hi>France.</hi> Blank Commiſsion to <hi>Lauderdail.</hi> Warrant to engage the Publick faith of the Kingdom for money abroad, and for Armes and Ammunition. A ſtrict union with <hi>Holland,</hi> for aſsiſting the proſecution of the Engagement. Promiſe to reſtore the Queen. <hi>Landerdails</hi> inſtruction to the Prince. Letters to the Queen, inviting her to return and to interpoſe. Letters to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and States of <hi>Holland,</hi> requiring Forraign aſsiſtance. Commiſsion to the Earl of <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth,</hi> Sir <hi>John Mackenzie,</hi> and all other Commiſsions for levying Forces. Act made at <hi>Stirling</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for bringing out all betwixt ſixty and ſixteen for their aſsiſtance. Act for giving to Sir <hi>Hary Gib</hi> two thouſand pound <hi>Stirling.</hi> Commiſsion for <hi>Innercauld</hi> his Regiment and watch. Act for aſsignments upon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178896:10"/>ſeverall Shires, for Maintenance and Exciſe, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>Galloway,</hi> and all others in that kinde. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the forfaultry of <hi>Midkeltoun.</hi> Warrants to admit to the Committees of War theſe that were in the firſt and ſecond Claſſes. Act for repaying money that was diſburſt for the Engagement. Aſsignation of the Exciſe to Captain <hi>Maine</hi> and Maſter <hi>Mauld.</hi> All others Acts done by theſe Members of the Committtee, who had taken the Oath before or after the firſt of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> at <hi>Stirling,</hi> or any where elſe, in proſecuting of the ſaid Engagement, and oppoſition to the Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Forces, riſen in defenſive Arms. And Ordains the ſame preſently to be publiſhed at the Mercat Croſſe of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and thereafter to be printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>William Scot,</hi> Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:178896:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178896:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
